Science serves as a powerful tool for unlocking the mysteries of the universe, but understanding its limitations is essential for its effective application.
科学是揭开宇宙奥秘的有力工具，但要有效运用科学，了解其局限至关重要。
There are occasions where I have used the handle of a knife as a hammer, but the result would have been better if I’d had a more suitable tool at hand.
我曾有几次把刀柄当锤子用，但如果当时手边有一件更合适的工具，效果本会更好。
As far as science goes, it is really good at testing things that are testable, but not so for those that are not.
就科学而言，它非常擅长检验可检验的事物，但对不可检验的事物就不是这样了。
We can do, and have done, an impressive amount with our brains.
凭借大脑，我们能够做成、也已经做成了数量惊人的事情。
But there are limits.
但局限是存在的。
Sometimes these limits go away if we keep at it for long enough — we just need better facilities and experiments to get the answer.
有时候，只要我们坚持足够长的时间，这些局限就会消失——我们只是需要更好的设施和实验来得到答案。
Breaking new ground in modern science this way can be costly.
以这种方式在现代科学中开辟新天地，代价可能很高。
Next-generation supercomputers or incredibly large telescopes are expensive, yet these may be required to find answers to some of the unsolved mysteries of the universe.
下一代超级计算机或超大型望远镜造价高昂，但要为宇宙中一些未解之谜找到答案，可能就需要它们。
Sometimes the limits we encounter in trying to unlock the nature of the universe are cognitive.
有时，我们在试图揭开宇宙本质的过程中遇到的局限是认知上的。
Think about this: human DNA is only about 1.2 percent different from that of chimps.
想想这一点：人类的DNA与黑猩猩的DNA只相差约1.2%。
Chimps are smart, no question.
黑猩猩很聪明，这一点毫无疑问。
But could you teach them advanced mathematics?
但你能教它们高等数学吗？
What if our DNA were another 1.2 percent further evolved than it is?
要是我们的DNA比现在再多进化1.2%，会怎么样？
What might our brains be capable of then?
到那时，我们的大脑可能会有怎样的能力呢？
The level of abstract thinking might be unimaginable.
抽象思维的水平可能会超乎想象。
Sometimes the limits we hit are fundamental.
有时，我们碰到的局限是根本性的。
There are laws of nature we may never be able to understand, however advanced our brains might become.
无论我们的大脑变得多么发达，有些自然法则我们也许永远都无法理解。
There are experiments we might never be able to perform.
有些实验我们也许永远都无法进行。
We may never be able to test what caused the universe to be created, and what caused the cause of the universe being created.
我们也许永远无法检验是什么导致宇宙被创造出来，以及这一起因本身又是由什么引起的。
This is where science may never break through.
这正是科学也许永远无法突破的地方。
For something to be considered scientific, it must, by definition, be testable.
按照定义，某样东西要被视为科学的，就必须是可检验的。
There is a problem here: it may not need to be testable right now, but it must be testable at some point in the future by experiment.
这里有个问题：它不必现在就能检验，但必须在将来的某个时候能够通过实验来检验。
If an idea is untestable, that doesn’t mean it is wrong.
如果一个想法无法检验，那并不意味着它是错误的。
It means it is untestable for now.
那只意味着它目前还无法检验。
These untestable ideas also happen to be some of the most interesting ones, probably because they’ve puzzled humanity for centuries.
这些无法检验的想法也恰好属于最有趣的想法之列，这可能是因为它们已经困扰了人类好几个世纪。